There's this really annoying pattern
that I see people do everywhere that I
think is making their AI coding output
worse, not better, and costing them
tokens. Now, most of the time when I let
AI explore my codebase, the only thing
AI has to go on is the code itself. And
it the code is supposed to be sort of
self-explanatory. It's supposed to be
have enough information in the code so
that AI can interpret it. That puts a
lot of burden on my code, so I need to
make sure my code is well-formatted,
that it's in the right file systems,
that it's organized into reasonable
chunks so the AI can look at it, that
there's interfaces and implementations
and they're separated so AI can just
take what it needs. However, a lot of
folks are not doing this. They are
taking a layer of docs, so they're
creating docs for their code and getting
the AI to primarily rely on those docs.
The issue I have with this is those
docs, like markdown files inside the
repository, they're usually not
executable. They're not testable against
the code. And so they can drift away
from the code. The docs can say one
thing, but the actual code, the source
of truth, can say another. And this is
really bad because if there are two
sources of truth and they conflict, then
AI won't know which one is the real one.
And so I consider this a really, really
big problem and a massive antipattern to
build this whole layer of docs just to
explain what the code can anyway. Now,
some people will read this and think
that I'm against all docs, that the only
thing you should have in your repo is
code. No, that's not true. Code should
be self-explanatory, but there are some
things that code can't explain. code
can't tell you what alternatives were
considered instead of the code that's
there. And so you need architectural
decision records in your repo to capture
those. It also can't really explain the
domain language that you're using to
work with your code. Does it know what
an order is in your codebase? Probably
not. And so a glossary is extremely
helpful. And finally, a thin layer of
docs just to navigate around the main
aspects of your code is really helpful
just to speed up AI's exploration of
your code. But the concept of docs as
the source of truth, as the thing that
you read to understand the code, no, I
don't like that at all.